Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, David H. Kurtzman (Acting), Administrative Files, 1966-1967 UA.2.10.1966-1967
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, David H. Kurtzman (Acting), Administrative Files
1966-1967
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor
UA.2.10.1966-1967
18.75 Linear Feet (45 boxes)
CONTENT WARNING -- This finding aid contains records that have been identified as including offensive, harmful, racist, or misrepresentative creator supplied language. In keeping with archival best practice, this language has been retained to preserve the context of the records. In keeping but acknowledging this language, A&SC hopes to encourage critical assessment and questioning of historical materials. Researchers should bear this in mind when accessing Administrative files of Acting University of Pittsburgh Chancellor David H. Kurtzman, 1966-1967.
Access Restrictions
Some restrictions: Box 1, FF 8 (Admission Letters).
Acquisition Information
These files were deposited at the archives by the Chancellor's office on December 3, 1968.
Previous Citation
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, David H. Kurtzman (Acting), Administrative Files, 1966-1967, UA.2.10.1966-1967, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Biography
Dr. David H. Kurtzman came to the University of Pittsburgh as its Vice Chancellor for Finance in July of 1965. He assumed his new duties at the height of a financial crisis at the University. Seven months later, the institution faced another crisis, the death of Acting Chancellor Stanton C. Crawford in 1966. Dr. Kurtzman was asked to serve as the Chancellor until the University named a permanent Chancellor. In his capacity as Acting Chancellor, Kurtzman guided the University through the transition to a state-related institution.
Scope and Content Notes
These are the administrative files of Acting Chancellor David H. Kurtzman, who assumed the position of Chancellor upon the death of Stanton C. Crawford. This collection includes the documentation of the University's transition to a state-related institution. Kurtzman served as acting chancellor from January 1966 through May 30, 1967. Wesley W. Posvar was appointed Chancellor on June 1, 1967.
University of Pittsburgh; Correspondence; Administrative records; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Administration; Kurtzman, David H. -- Records and correspondence; University of Pittsburgh -- Administration; University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor -- Records and correspondence
- A (General) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Dr. Kurtzman's appointment book for 1966; Association of American Colleges; American Council on Education. An assessment of quality in graduate education; Also letter to the Trustees concerning this publication
- American Council on Education (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Federal investment in higher education; 1967; Fair Labor Standards amendments of 1966; Brief statement of programs and activities, 1966; Improving college teaching; Aids and impediments; Analysis of new education bills, 1967; Record requirements and exemptions under minimum wage amendments, 1967.
- Agency for International Development (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Correspondence
- American Association of University Professors (Box 1, Folder 4)
  AAUP Salary survey, February 1967; Economic status of the profession; Report on the self-grading compensation survey, 1965-66.
- Association of Urban Universities (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Academic Disciplines, Vice Chancellor (Charles Peake) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Growth of Departmental professional staffs vs. enrollment increases, 1967; Trip to Asia, by Charles H. Peake; Boschan letter and library, 1966; Enrollment estimates, 1967/68; Medical Technology program, 1966; Space needs in the Cathedral of Learning; Teaching in the School of General Studies; Chemistry Department and the Development Program, Cost study, The Academic Disciplines, June 2, 1966 (extensive); Building needs of the Academic Disciplines under "State-Related" status, May 5, 1966; Enrollment projections; Suggestion for budget economy; Department of Philosophy
- Admissions and Student Aid (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Admission of physically handicapped students; Statement to Courier concerning admission policy of the School of Medicine; Admission policy concerning regional campuses; Statistical distribution of Freshmen, 1966; Staff report on loan and scholarship study of the Health and Welfare Association of Allegheny County, 1966; Admissions-policy projections
- Admissions Letters (A-Z) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Admissions reports, December 1965-December 16, 1966; Letters to and from parents and students
- Africa, University Presidents Conference (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Allegheny Conference on Community Development (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Allied Health Professions (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Proposal for formation of a School of Health Related Professions, 1967
- Alumni Activities (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Correspondence; Special reports; Minutes of Alumni Council meetings; Plan for a mail questionnaire to measure extent to which alumni programs induced alumni financial support, 1965
- Anthropology Department (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Space needs, Laboratories
- Aspen Corporation (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Information retrieval for Laws, Statues, Judicial Decisions and ordinances; negotiations and contract; Also the Times Mirror Co., Los Angeles, Automated Law searching
- Assistant to the Chancellor, Robert H. Bailie (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Athletics (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Prowling Panther Club, 1966; Stadium Authority; Sports Illustrated; Football coaches of the year clinic, 1967; A basic weight-training program; Dave Hart's suggestions for Improvement of Football program, 1966; Team lists for Fall term, 1966/67 (Football, Soccer, Track); Need for a full-time recruiter; WWSW Radio, Inc.; Football recruiting
- Athletics, Football (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Academic statistics, 1965/66; Study of Pitt's future in football, 1967-1976; 1965: Present and future status of Intercollegiate program, from Athletic Committee; General correspondence, 1965; Individual games, 1965, 1966
- Auxiliary Enterprises, Director of (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Bruce Hall (as dormitory); Book Store, 1967; Profit & loss statements, August 1966-May 1967, for Auxiliary enterprises; Nurses Residence apartments
- A (General) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  American Institute of Indian Studies; Allegheny Observatory; Report of the recent survey of the Pittsburgh Police Bureau by The International Association of the Chiefs of Police, by David W. Craig, 1967; Civil Liberties Union; American Association of Collegiate Schools of Business. Constitution, By-Laws, 1966/67; University of Pittsburgh School of Pharmacy, Report to American Council on Pharmaceutical Education, March 1966; Kurtzman, David H. A city university's multi-million dollar plant expansion, 1967 [articles] McDowell, John B. Summary of Problems of administering a private school system, F 1967; Prasse, Arthur T. Problems of prison administration in Pennsylvania. 1966; Steadman, Robert F. Modernizing Local Government, 1966
- Board of Trustees, Alumni Affairs Committee (Box 4, Folder 20)
  American Civil Liberties Union and House Un-American Activities Committee; Allegheny Observatory; various associations
- Board of Trustees, Budget Audit Committee (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Board of Trustees, Bylaws Committee (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Minutes; Brief history of appointment and tenure plan, Oct. 1966
- Board of Trustees, Educational Policies Committee (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Related Material
  Minutes, 1965, May 1966; Concepts of Program for the University, 1960; Minutes, Joint Meeting of the Educational Policies Committee of the Board of Trustees and the Educational Policies Committee of the University Senate
- Board of Trustees, Executive Committee (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Minutes, 1966/67; Balance sheet, October 31, 1966
- Board of Trustees, Executive Committee (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Minutes, January –October 1966
- Board of Trustees, Executive Committee (Box 5, Folder 26)
  Minutes, 1965. Index to Minutes, 1964-65
- Board of Trustees, Finance Committee (Box 5, Folder 27)
  Accounts…and Minutes of meetings, 1966-1967
- Board of Trustees, Finance Committee (Box 5, Folder 28)
  Financial statements, 1966
- Board of Trustees, Fraternity Housing (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Board of Trustees, General (Box 6, Folder 30)
  Commencement remarks, Kurtzman, June 6, 1966; Enrollment projections through 1976; Bylaws, 1964;BOT members 1965-1967
- Board of Trustees, Honorary Degrees (Box 6, Folder 31)
  List of possible awardees; list of those nominated for honorary degrees for the June 1966 commencement and the October 1966 Fall convocation
- Board of Trustees, Individual members' files (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Board of Trustees, Nominating Committee (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Board of Trustees, Physical Plant and Site Development Committee (Box 6, Folder 34)
  Building programs as of October 1, 1965; Minutes of meetings, 1966-67
- Board of Trustees, Planning and Development Committee (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Board of Trustees, Resolutions (Box 6, Folder 36)
  State Related resolution; Change of name, 1966; New degree in School of Education (Master of Arts in Teaching); Change in tuition; Graduates, Number 1967; Loan agreements; Armory site; Deaths
- Book Center (Box 6, Folder 37)
  Statements; Memos; Campus Store; Student appeal
- Bradford Campus (Box 7, Folder 38)
  Summary of operations; Expansion; Advisory Board
- Budget, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 39)
- Business, Graduate School of (Box 7, Folder 40-43)
  Memos to & from the Dean; Frederick, William C.; Advisory Council; Ford Foundation Grant (Matching grants); Undergraduate School of Business
- Business Systems and Data Processing, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 44)
- B (General) (Box 7, Folder 45)
  Microbial, Molecular & Biophysics Department, 1966; Board of County Commissioners – on relationship with state, 1966; Brennan Brothers – Holland House plastering
- Calendar, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 46)
- Capital Budget (Box 7, Folder 47)
- Carnegie Institute of Technology (Box 7, Folder 48)
  Carnegie-Mellon merger, 1966; Cooperation, 1966
- Center for Regional Economic Studies (Box 7, Folder 49)
  Hoover, Dr. Edgar M. 1965
- Chancellor Search Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  Faculty Committee; Trustee Committee, 1966
- Chancellor, Acting (Box 7, Folder 51)
  Memos; Administrative reorganization – March 1966; Postage meters
- Chancellor, Acting (Box 8, Folder 52)
  Edison Montgomery 2/26-3/15/1967; 1968/69 budget; Audit group; Commencement speaker; Oakland Corp.; International Dimensions
- Chancellor's Staff Meetings, September 1965-May 1967 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  Minutes, 1965/67; Administrative affairs; buildings, commencement, honorary degree recipients, Posvar's visit, Gwilym Price to retire, trimester
- Chancellor's Meetings with Students (Box 8, Folder 54)
- City Planning Commission (Box 8, Folder 55)
- Clinical Chemistry Laboratory (Box 8, Folder 56)
- Commencement, May 31, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  1967 (holograph letter from Andrew Wyeth); pictures of Honorary degree recipients (moved to photo file 9/13/84); address by Chancellor Kurtzman; Program; Article by Finney
- Commencement, June 6, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  Honorary degrees (Magee, Marland, Rea, Stever); Address; Remarks; Guests
- Commencement, June 7, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  1965; Appalachia theme; Memo on "War on Poverty"
- Clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 60)
- Common Facilities Building (Box 8, Folder 61)
  Bids and Naming of David Lawrence Hall
- Comptroller and Assistant Treasurer, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 62)
- Comptroller and Assistant Treasurer, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  Plant fund Project Accounts; Debt bonds; Textbook exemption from sales tax; Central Pharmacy from Scaife Hall to Eye & Ear Hospital
- Computer Center, 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  Proposed program for a M.S. degree in Computer Science, December 1966; Computer Equipment Committee – equipment in each place; name changed from Computation and Data Processing Center
- Condolence Letters, 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 65)
- Continuing Education (Box 9, Folder 66)
- Honors Convocation, March 16, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  William Steinburg honored; Chancellors remarks
- Counseling Center (Box 9, Folder 69)
  Mystique of the College Athlete by George E. Letchworth
- Crawford, Stanton C., 1966 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  Concerning his death, January 26, 1966; ground breaking for Crawford Hall
- Cultural and Educational Exchange (Box 9, Folder 70)
  Faculty applications for grants for study abroad; David L. Lawrence Scholarship Fund; Faculty Fullbright awards; Israeli Nationality for Foreign Student Office; Enrollment from abroad, Fall 1965/66 (directory)
- C (General) (Box 9, Folder 71)
  Correspondence & memos: Louis Caplan Human Relations Award; College Entrance Examination Board; Cooperative program in economics and industrial management
- Deans, Council of (Box 10, Folder 72)
  Paper by Dean James Kehl, "Reflections on the Graduate Student in Undergraduate instruction." Rosters; Policy to present conflict of interest in government sponsored research at the University of Pittsburgh
- Dental Clinic (Box 10, Folder 73)
  Planned use of building for Anthropology and Physics
- Dental Medicine, School of (Box 10, Folder 74)
  Name changed from School of Dentistry; Degree granted changed; DDs now DMD; Board of Visitors; New building for Dentistry, 1967; dedication; Evaluation report of the Council on Dental Education, American Dental Association; Dental education, Dental hygiene, Dental assisting education
- Development Programs (Box 10, Folder 75)
  Century Club development programs; Annual Giving Fund; Ten Year development needs from Acting Chancellor; University development-preliminary estimates, draft 10/12/66 (confidential)
- Development, Vice Chancellor for (Box 10, Folder 76)
- Discrimination (Box 10, Folder 77)
  Policies against, 1962-67
- Dormitories, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 78)
  Charges; Correspondence with Department of Public Instruction; Income and expense; Dormitory priorities
- D (General) (Box 10, Folder 79)
  Danforth Foundation, J. Richard Dillon
- Economics, Department of (Box 10, Folder 80)
  Statement of Professor Mark Perlman before the House Bi-partisan Committee to investigate employment and unemployment in Pennsylvania. 1966
- Ecuador Project (Box 11, Folder 81-82)
  US AID Project with Central University, Quito; Reports on progress; Dr. Blaise replaced Dr. Schaefer; Program of collaboration; Quarterly reports
- Education, School of (Box 11, Folder 83)
  Board of Visitors; Patterns of appropriations for institutions of higher education by General Assembly of Pennsylvania, 1965-66; Recruiting Black professors for teaching positions, January 1967; Memorandum of agreement for vocational and technical teacher education and related activities by the University of Pittsburgh and the commonwealth, Higher Education Act of 1965
- Educational Policies Committee (Box 11, Folder 84)
- EDUCOM (Box 11, Folder 85)
  Concerning making Pittsburgh its base; Edison Montgomery as its President; History
- Engineering, School of (Box 11, Folder 86)
  Engineers' Week 3/16-17, 1966; Groundbreaking ceremonies, Logan Armory, March 16, 1966; Honorary degree (Maxime Faget); Michael Benedum Engineering Building; Engineering at Pitt (14 p.); Alumni Directory: Chemical & Petroleum Engineering; Paper: The Omitted Link, by H.E. Hoelscher. 1967. 12p.; Organizational charts for School of Engineering; Junior Engineers' and Scientists' Summer Institute; Name change to School of Engineering, 1965
- English, Department of (Box 12, Folder 87)
  Correspondence concerning Professors Philbrick and Markman
- Enrollment (Box 12, Folder 88)
  Kurtzman's 1966/67; percentage of male & female, 1965 and 1966; percentage of out-of-state, 1966 Fall; Projected 1966/67 – 1975/76
- Equality of Educational Opportunity (Box 12, Folder 89)
- E (General) (Box 12, Folder 90)
  Correspondence. "A twentieth century approach to judicial administration, by Judge Henry Ellenbogen, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny Co., Pittsburgh, PA; Research and Development Centers, May 1966; Selected educational statistics for the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, 1966; Automation benefits the courts; address by Judge Henry Ellenbogen, April 4, 1966; Excerpta Medica Foundation
- Faculty (Box 12, Folder 91)
  Salary schedules, Sabbaticals, Data and Teaching Load, Manual
- Faculty Club (Box 12, Folder 92)
  Relocation, Liquor policy
- Faculty Committee on Faculty Standards (Box 12, Folder 93)
  History of Appointment and Tenure, October 1966; Suggested changes in Chapter II. "The Faculty" by laws of the Board of Trustees, 1966' Meeting cancelled June, 1965; Orientation list
- Faculty Terminations (Box 12, Folder 95)
- Falk Clinic (Box 12, Folder 95)
  Falk building renovations, 1966; Business arrangements
- File outline (Box 12, Folder 97)
- Finance, Assistant Vice Chancellor (Smith) (Box 12, Folder 98)
  Tuition and fees schedule, 1967; Financial statements; Closing Venetian Room; Bellefield Dwelling; Food service changes; Check cashing; Unrestricted gifts; Code of accounts; Accounting, Mechanization of; Trimester vs. Semester and Summer Session
- Finance, Vice Chancellor for (Box 13, Folder 99-100)
  Search for a new VC; Staggered salary increases, Financial statements, 1964/65; Personnel action; Equipment expenditures; Rugs, use of; Berwind-White Coal Mining Co. – deed; A "Program for improving the effectiveness of the financial function", March 28, 1966
- Fine Arts Department (Box 13, Folder 101)
  J.C. Leff collection; About new building; Miss Virginia Lewis resigned; Letter of Professor Leonard J. Slatkes in which he resigned
- Forbes Field (Box 13, Folder 102)
  Leased to Pittsburgh Athletic Company, Inc.
- Forbes Quadrangle (Box 13, Folder 103)
  Classroom requirements to 1976; renamed Posvar Hall on May 9, 2000
- Stephen Foster Memorial (Box 13, Folder 104)
  Tuesday Musical Club and its relationship to the building; University Theater; Ralph Allen
- Fraternities (Box 13, Folder 105)
  Housing problems
- Fund Raising (Box 13, Folder 106)
  State related status
- Restricted and Unrestricted Funds (Box 13, Folder 107)
  Use of cash for debt; correspondence with Patterson, Crawford, Arensberg & Dunn; 1964-1965
- F (General) (Box 13, Folder 108)
  Falk Professor of political science – 1965/66 Seminar in Politics; Making education relevant, by Marvin J. Feldman (Ford Foundation) 1966
- Geise, John Jacob (Box 13, Folder 109)
  Military research contracts
- General State Authority (Box 13, Folder 110)
  Playing Fields near Robinson Street; Quadrangle building plans; Annual Report, 1966 of GSA; Dental School building
- General Studies, School of (Box 13, Folder 111)
  Space problems – Cathedral of Learning 4th library floor stacks area; Proposal for Continuing Education Center, 1966; Clipping on International Conference of University Adult Education in Denmark, 1965
- Graduate Faculty (Box 13, Folder 112)
  Academic Organization, Draft report on by Putnam F. Jones, 1966 – reorganization plan; University Council on Graduate Study: Meetings of Council, 1966-67; Discussion of Ph.D. programs of different schools; Development needs for post-doctoral program; Policy for post-doctoral work; NASA training grant, annual report, 1965/66 & Supplement 1 & Supplement no. 2; Proposal to NASA for pre-doctoral research training grants, August 22, 1966 (12p.); Graduate Fellowships (NDEA)
- Greensburg Campus (Box 13, Folder 113)
  Fund raising campaign; Kick-off dinner, 1965; Greensburg Advisory Board; Renovation of Lynch Estate for use by the University
- Guatemala (Box 14, Folder unknown container)
  Report from San Carlos, March 1, 1967; Dr. Marshall Bernard Gunselman's Curriculum Vitae, December 1966; Report on status of Guatemala – to establish an instructional materials laboratory, new texts for students, and for training professors in methods & materials. 1966
- G (General) (Box 14, Folder 115)
  Galbraith, J.K. – biographical material; and other correspondence; Correspondence: Graves, Gill, Gladfelter, Gold, and others.
- Head Start Orientation Program (Box 14, Folder 116)
- Health Center Parking Garage (Lothrop Street) (Box 14, Folder 117)
- Health Law Center (Box 14, Folder 118)
  "Questions and answers concerning the Health Law Center's Legislative Service Program, September 1966"; memo on Wright
- Health Center (Box 14, Folder 119 A-B)
  University Health Center Board of Trustees, Minutes, 1967; Grant for Regional Medical Program, February 1967; Planning the Regional Medical Program in Western Pennsylvania (thick notebook); Health Center Hospital Service Corp.; Board of directors meeting, 1966; Board of Trustees meeting, 1966; Detailed report on examination balance sheet, June 30, 1966; Laundry question
- Health, Education and Welfare, U.S. Department of (Box 14, Folder 120)
  National Technical Institute for the Deaf ,1966; Work-study program, 1966; National Defense Student Loans; Fellowships under the National Defense Education Act of 1958
- Health, Education and Welfare Grants (Box 14, Folder 121)
  Natural Sciences Division, 1966; N.I.H. grant; Activities of Dr. John Geise which are divided among others 1966
- Health Related Professions, School of (Box 14, Folder 122)
  Correspondence about establishing, 1967
- Health Professions, Vice Chancellor for (Box 14, Folder 123-124)
  Appointment of Dr. Cheever, April 1967; Nurses Residence to remain with the University for present, 1966; Search Committee for V/C for 1966; Ecuador reconnaissance
- Health Professions, School of (Box 14, Folder 125)
  Clinical research involving human subjects; Proposed contract between the Presbyterian-University Hospital, Pittsburgh Skin & Cancer Foundation and the University, 1966
- Heinz Memorial Chapel (Box 15, Folder 126)
  New roof needed, 1967; New organ needed, 1967; Policies, 1966 Christmas music
- Hill Education Project (Box 15, Folder 127)
- Higher Education Committee (Box 15, Folder 128)
  Subcommittee to investigate possible establishment of a State University in Western Pennsylvania, 1965
- Higer Education Act of 1965 (Box 15, Folder 129)
  Title I; Proposals for requests; Public law 89-329; Title I – VII
- Higher Education (Box 15, Folder 130)
  "The Compact for Education; views from Higher Education", International Education Act of 1966; Financial assistance for construction of higher education facilities, Act of 1963, amended through February 8, 1966; Report of the Higher Education Committee of Pennsylvania House of Representatives 1965/66
- Hillman Library (Box 15, Folder 131)
  About construction, 1965; Hillman gift; Furnishing by Dolores Miller and Associates; Plan of Library; 1960 letter concerning acquiring land; Stark, Thralls, Educational Communications Center
- Honorary Degrees (Box 15, Folder 132)
  Lists; Awarded to Mrs. Ruth Crawford Mitchell (lists of her activities); Honorary degree to Louis Caplan
- Hospital Council of Western Pennsylvania (Box 15, Folder 133)
  Report of Committee to review wage practices in western Pennsylvania hospitals, 1967; Compensation practices…1967
- Hospitals (Box 15, Folder 134-135)
  Children's Eye; Eye & Ear; Presbyterian-University-Comparison of budget to actual results of operations, June-July 1967-; Minutes of Board of Trustees of Presbyterian January-April-May April-July 1967; Proposed budget, 1967/68; 1966/67. Minutes of Executive meetings; Nurses Residence
- House and Senate Bills (Box 16, Folder 136)
  Comprehensive Planning and Coordination Act. of 1967; University of Pittsburgh as state-related; International Education Act. of 1966; Unemployment Insurance Act; Health Law Center